בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is דף י"ח, daf Yud-Chet,
י"ז, Yud-Zayin, of course י"ז, Yud-Zayin, I don't know why I'm always
a דף daf ahead. As I was saying, today's דף י"ז, daf
Yud-Zayin, and we pick up at the bottom at the two dots
about five lines before the lines get wide. We had been
discussing the משנה mishna that spoke about selling them various
types of wild animals and that led to the whole גמרא Gemara's
discussion
about whether חיות chayas are included in the prohibition. But alright, fundamentally
that was just introducing don't selling them wild animals and then, which
is sort of not similar to the discussion about weapons, but this
is a little different, this is about just the fact that not
that they consciously use them to do violence, but that they might
not sort of take care of the wild animals, we might not
take care of the wild animals either, we're not allowed to keep
them, but then we shouldn't be selling them to the non-Jews either.
Then we get to a new point also relating to the issue
about violence, which is don't build a basilica, a type of a
platform in which the judges sit, a scaffold in which they do
their executions, because the Roman government obviously executed, crucified actually as well,
a lot of Jews under its control, so therefore helping it build
these buildings in which their judgment is done was seen as aiding
and abetting the way in which they would use violence against the
Jewish people.
And also stadia, which like that plural of stadium, it might be
wrong though anyway, stadiums, but I think it's stadia, אצטדיא astadya anyway
in which they would have these gladiator games. Okay, so now we
pick up with, so let's pick up with that, five lines before
the lines get wide.
אין בונים. Ein bonim. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר רבי יוחנן:
Amar Rabbah bar Bar Chana Amar Rabbi Yochanan: ג' בסילקאות הן: Gimmel
basilka'ot hein: של מלכי עובדי כוכבים, shel malchei ovdei chochavim, there is
one that's a type of a place in which kings live, a
castle, ושל מרחצאות, veshel merchata'ot, there's a type of a basilica that's
in the context of a bathhouse, I don't know exactly what that
is, I assume if I knew Roman history better I would understand
this better, ושל אוצרות, veshel otzarot, and ones that are used in
the context of some type of a storage city, storage location. Anyway,
none of them seem to be particularly problematic. So אמר רבא: Amar
Rava: ב' להיתר וחד לאיסור. Beis leheter vechad le'issur. Two of them
you're allowed to build and one you're not. So בסימן לאסור מלכיהם
בזיקים, besiman leesore malkeihem bezikim, to bind up their kings with ropes,
so לאסור, leesore, it's אסור, assur, right, the same word, to bind.
Whereas מתיר matir means to be free from bounds, to be permissible.
So anyway the one of the kings is forbidden because in the
one of the kings that's where judgments would take place. So that's
like the courthouse. Okay, so that's why that's forbidden.
So the
גמרא Gemara says: והתנן אין בונים עמהם בסילקי גרדום אצטדיא ובימה. Vehatnan
ein bonim imahem basilki gardom istadya ubima. One of the things on
those lists in addition to the scaffold and the platform, whatever, is
the basilica, which presumably is the place in which the courthouse. So
אימא: eima: של גרדום ושל אצטדיא ושל בימה. shel gardom veshel istadya
veshel bima. בסילקי Basilki there is not by itself. A basilica of
a judging platform, in which judgment is done, a basilica in which
this platform takes place, this scaffold exists, in which this bathhouse exists,
etc. etc. Okay, so that's the question: is there really a basilica
that's not of the other specific things mentioned in the משנה mishna
that is forbidden? Alright, fine. Now before we get to the next
thing because now we're going to get into some very famous and
very powerful like מדרש midrash or whatever stories, I don't know if
I'd call it מדרש, midrash, anyway, אגדתא, aggadta, I just want to
read you from the middle of this תוספות Tosafos that I mentioned
yesterday, what is this בימוסאות bimosot where רש"י Rashi says it means
a altar on which they would bring offerings to עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. And רש"י Rashi says well actually you can build that, it's
two degrees removed. And like what? Sounds like it's one degree removed,
doesn't it sound like it's two degrees removed? I mean it's not
the sacrifice itself. You don't put the עבודה זרה avodah zarah on
the altar, you put the sacrifice on the altar but you use
the altar in an act of worship to the עבודה זרה. avodah
zarah. So תוספות Tosafos also is like astounded by this. So if
you look at the middle of this תוספות בימוסאות, Tosafos bimosot, תוספות
Tosafos says the following, he says if you look almost exactly in
the middle he
says אלמא almah line starts with the word אלמא, almah, it's like
literally in the exact middle of that תוספות בימוסאות, Tosafos bimosot, he
says אמה ממש. ammah mamish. אלמא ממש תשמיש עבודת כוכבים עצמו הוא.
alma mamash tashmish avodat kochavim atzmo hu. Don’t tell me this is
two degrees removed and altar used to offer offerings is one degree
removed. It’s a תשמיש. tashmish. What more of a תשמיש tashmish of
עבודה זרה avodah zarah can you think of than an altar? ועוד
Ve'od says תוספות, Tosafot, I love this line, דנהי נמי דמשמש דמשמש
עבודה זרה. dinehi nami demishamesh demishamesh avodah zarah.
Let’s say from a technical formalistic point of view we'll call it
a two degrees removed. It serves the sacrifice and the sacrifice serves
the- serves the- serves the idol. It’s not directly do- you know
connected to the idol, it's connected to the sacrifice, etc. Let’s say
I would technically agree with you that it’s two degrees removed. אטו
לבנות עמהם? Atu livnot imahem? How- like, you know, here's like some
religious sensibility, how- even if some formalistic way that's true, how could
you think you could build this altar? וכי יש סברא להתיר לבנות
עמהם מקום שיקטירו עליו במחתה לעבודה זרה? Vechi yesh sevara lehatir livnot
imahem makom sheyaktiru alav bemachta la'avodah zarah?
Is there any- anybody who would think that it would be permissible
to like create an altar on which you would bring some incense
to עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? Like your religious sensibility sometimes has- you
know have to say don't give me some technical halachic point that
it's two degrees removed. Like how could any פרומ frum Jew think
they could build an altar to עבודה זרה? avodah zarah? And therefore
he
says לכך נראה לי Lekach nireh li גרסת רש"י girsat Rashi דדימוסיאות,
dedimosiyot, it's דדימוסיאות dedimosiyot with a ד daled not בימוסיאות bimosiyot and
that actually is once again a- that's a bathhouse. Similar to the
other discussion and the bathhouse issue had to deal with not a
place of violence or judgment, but the bathhouse ish- issue had to
deal with the fact that they would sometimes, you know they would
put idols in the bathhouse ודימוסיאות ומרחצאות. vedimosiyot umerchatza'ot.
What? Oh so- well the משנה Mishnah says... Oh right. Because it's
בונה עמהם, boneh imahem, you're allowed to build a בימוסיאות bimosiyot ובית
מרחצאות. bet merchatza'ot.
Right, so it's between that and- no-
oh
you mean why do you have to say it twice? Yeah, I
don't know, I'm sure there're different types of bathhouses. Okay, so- so
even though the bathhouses have some apse or whatever it's called nave
or whatever for the altar, okay, for the idol, that's not forbidden,
it's fundamentally a bathhouse, and as the משנה Mishnah says, when you
get to that place for the altar, you don't build the actual,
you know, niche in which the altar is put, but fundamentally you
can build the bathhouse. We're talking here about bathhouses, we are not
talking about altars for עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Okay, yeah.
Yeah, I would have thought maybe it meant like little ones, like,
you know, you have the- you have the real one that- that
use it and then others like more decorative altars that they don't
use.
Okay, but that's not how רש"י Rashi says. Alright, let's go now
look at the גמרא, Gemara, two lines down in the wide line.
תנו רבנן. Tanu rabanan. כשנתפס רבי אליעזר למינות. Keshenitpas Rabbi Eliezer leminut.
Okay, when רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was seized by the Roman government
for suspicion of heresy. Now you would ask me, why does the
Roman government care that a- they think a Jew is a heretic?
So מינות, minut, as you know from the many- from the time
you have spent with me, very often means Jewish Christians. So, and
the Romans, as you may or may not know, I assume you
do know, you know, Jews were not the only ones who were
oppressed and persecuted by the Romans, also the early Christians were. You
know, they have a whole earth history of- of martyrdom, that they
were also, you know, executed by the Roman government. They had a,
you know, their religion was even more disturbing, it was like more
revolutionary, you know, than the- you know, in terms of believ- belief
of the coming etc. and overthrow of the- of the current gov-
you know, Roman government etc. so it was seen- it was a
king, right? You know, so- they believ- so therefore that was seen
as very threatening. So early Christians were- and they also, like you
know the phrase give unto Caesar what is Caesar's? You- ever hear
that? You know, because the whole question was could Christians give the
sort of tribute to the Caesar or wasn't Caesar's fashion themselves as
gods, was that seen as a type of עבודה זרה? avodah zarah?
You know, they had the same type of a question. Anyway, so
there's all this history of early Christianity and whether they would or
would not submit to certain types
of rules of the Romans and that the martyrdom of- and that
they were often martyred by- by the Romans. So, anybody know the
secret signal for- for the Christians to know somebody's a fellow Christian?
A fish. I don't know why it is, but
anyway.
The fish would be the secret signal so that- you know within,
right... ICTHYS.
Yeah, ICTHYS, yeah, ICTHYS, yes, to this...
I'm sure that's why it was, but it was the secret signal
so that you could identify a fellow Christian when it was sort
of dangerous to be a Christian.
Okay, so anyway, so the Romans- so- so the Romans therefore suspected
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer of- like you- have- until now had been,
like you know we knew you were a Jew, Jews are fine,
okay, you know, there was Hadrian, we had some issues with them
before. But anyway, okay. But, you know, now we're cool with you
guys. Oh, but now we suspect that maybe you're a heretic, meaning
you've become a Jewish Christian, which is the dangerous religion at this
point, and therefore they were going to execute him for being a
Christian. Okay, so this is the story. Now,
the reason presumably we're dealing with this here is because you don't
build these בית משפט, bet mishpat, you know, these sort of courthouses
for the Romans. because of the way they persecute, you know, the
Jews or they judge the Jews and they execute Jews, some trumped-up
charges, false charges, whatever, whether they believe they were true, didn't believe
they were true. So in that context about how the Romans falsely
judge the Jews, okay, and why you don't participate or harshly judge,
whatever, execute Jews in the context of their courthouses, we're having this
story.
Okay, so I wonder if it also informed our whole construct of
the סנהדרין, Sanhedrin, you know, the predilection for זכות zechut versus חובה?
chovah?
Could be. Right, that's right, in addition to sort of internal reasons,
right. כשנתפס רבי אליעזר למינות, Keshenitfas Rabbi Eliezer l'minut, so when he
was seized in suspicion of heresy, העלוהו לגרדום, He'aluho l'gardom, and here's
that word גרדום, gardom, right? They brought him up to the גרדום,
gardom, okay, לדון, lidon, to be judged. So you see the גרדום
gardom is that type of a platform in which the judges sit
where the convict or where the suspected person is, you know, is
judged. Okay, וגרדום לדון. v'gardom lidon. אמר לו, Amar lo, אמר לו
אותו הגמון, amar lo oto hegmon, so
the הגמון hegmon said, the officer, the head judge said:
זקן שכמותך יעסוק בדברים בטלים הללו? Zaken shekmotecha ya'asok bidvarim betelim halalu?
Somebody who or בדברים הללו, bidvarim halalu, somebody, you know, you're a
good old פרום frum Jew, you're a
sage. Why are you involving yourself in this heretical sect, these Christians,
you know, what has led you to go ahead and be, you
know, and to
follow them? So אמר לו, amar lo, so he said to him:
נאמן עלי הדיין. Ne'eman alai hadayan. The judge is trusted, you know,
I trust in the judge.
So because he meant in God
we trust, I trust that God will vindicate me. Okay, but he
was intentionally, you know, these also these stories we're going to read
are also about how the rabbis were very smart and managed to
sort of get out of these situations. So קסבר אותו הגמון עליו
הוא אומר. Kasavar oto hegmon alav hu omer. Oh, he says he
trusts me. I trust the judge to know that I am innocent
and these charges are false. So
the actual judge said, oh, yeah, he has trust in me, he
trusts my judgment. So עליו הוא
אומר. Alav hu omer. והוא לא אמר אלא כנגד אביו שבשמים. V'hu
lo amar ela keneged aviv shebashamayim. He was referring to God. אמר
לו, Amar lo, הואיל והאמנתי עליך, ho'il v'hemanti alecha, since you said
that you just, you know, you're not going to try to defend
yourself, you're not going to try to bring witnesses, since you said
you trusted me to make the right judgment about you, האמנתי עליך,
hemanti alecha, right, you trusted me to make the right judgment about
you, דימוס פטור אתה. Dimus patur ata. So now this is interesting
because we had the word before, right, דימוס dimus according to תוספות.
Tosafot. What is this word דימוס?
dimus? Sounds like a dismissal.
So yeah, so if you look at רשי, Rashi, דימוס פטור אתה,
Dimus patur ata, דימוס היא היתה שם יראתו. Dimus hi hayta shem
yirato. So רשי Rashi says it was a name of his God.
Actually, if you take a look in whatever,
I didn't look in Steinsaltz, thank you, I looked in Soncino, and
Soncino had, now you're right, I was just trying to say that
I did look in Steinsaltz. It's interesting what Steinsaltz says. Anyway, he
says it's some word that sounds like, you know, basically it means
you are exempt, almost like dismissed. Freedom? Freedom he says it means?
Okay, freedom, exempt, I exempt you. תוספות Tosafot actually gets it. תוספות
Tosafot says דימוס פטור אתה, Dimus patur ata, פירש ברחמי, perash berachamei,
עבודת כוכבים שלו, avodat kochavim shelo, כי דימוס ki dimus bracket עבודת
כוכבים שלו. avodat kochavim shelo. The point is כי דימוס לשון רחמים
היא. ki dimus lashon rachamim hi. So you're exempt, you're exonerated, mercy
or something like that, you're free. Okay, so you're free, fine, you
trusted me, you said you're innocent and you said that you would
trust me to see that, fine, you're exempt. Yes.
Is it just for modern Hebrew? Yes. So גרדום gardom is like
a place of execution? Oh, interesting.
Or עלי גרדום Alei Gardom in Akko where the Irgun were hung,
yeah, the British.
And דימוס dimus is used like for somebody who is retired or
let's say somebody who was a judge and now he's שופט בדימוס.
shofet bedimus.
Oh, used
to be but now he's I don't know
what do you call them? Right, right, right. Oh I see, I
see.
Like past, president, בדימוס, bedimus, president.
Interesting, interesting. Okay, very interesting. Okay. Alright, so just another
thing.
So why him?
Well, let's take a look.
כשבא לביתו
נכנסו תלמידיו אצלו לנחמו.
Kesheba
l'veito nichnesu talmidav etzlo lenachamo.
So when he came home, all of his students gathered around him
to console him. Not that he had survived, obviously everyone was thrilled
that he had survived, but that he was seized on false charges.
ולא קיבל עליו תנחומים. V'lo kibel alav tanchumim. He refused to accept
it. It deeply bothered him that something that he had done had
led to the suspicion. So he was deeply, you know, he was
deeply bothered by this and nobody could say oh don't worry it's
all trumped up, like he was saying what did I do to
deserve this or what did I do you know to either that
God brought this upon me or what did I do in practice
that made the Romans think this? Okay. אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar
lo Rabbi Akiva, רבי, Rebbi, Rabbi Akiva said, רבי תרשיני לומר דבר
אחד ממה שלימדתני. Rebbi tarsheni lomar davar echad mimah shelimadtani. Allow me
to say something that I— אמר לו רבי עקיבא, Amar lo Rabbi
Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva said, רבי, Rebbe, הרשני לומר דבר אחד
ממה שלמדתני. harshini lomar davar echad mima shelimadtani. Allow me to say
something from what you have taught me. This actually very interesting right
now in like pastoral counseling we're talking about, you know, this with
students about like sometimes the importance to ask somebody for permission. Like
if somebody is sharing something with you and you say, would you
allow me to share some of my thoughts about this with you?
You know, so if it's like a sensitive issue. So, you know,
and that sort of sets a different tone.
So, would you permit me to share with something that? So then
you're not lecturing to the person when you've asked permission. Okay. So
permit me to share something. אמר לו, Amar lo, אמר לו אמור.
Amar lo emor. Yes, please say. אמר לו רבי, Amar lo Rebbe,
שמא מינות
בא לידך והנאה, shema minut ba leyadcha vehana'ah, maybe, you know, some
heretical teaching, you know, some you encountered some heretical teaching, literally it
came into your hand, and you actually you got some pleasure from
it. You know, so, you know, oh, you know, maybe you some
teaching, oh, that's a good insight, you
know. ועלב נתפסת, ve'alav nitpasta, and that is what led you to
be seized. It's sort of like a double meaning here, meaning maybe,
you know, you've engaged some of these heretics, maybe you sort of
thought like oh interesting intellectual kind of discussion with them about how
do you read this source or how I read this source or
whatever, you know, and that both could have led the Romans to
think that you were involved in it, that you were a follower,
and also maybe that's why you're being punished by God because you
should be keeping away from it. So there's like a double meaning
to how this is explaining what happened. Okay. אמר לו, Amar lo,
עקיבא, Akiva, עקיבא הזכרתני, Akiva hizkartani, you reminded me. פעם אחת הייתי
מהלך בשוק עליון של ציפורי, pa'am achat hayiti mehalech beshuk elyon shel
Tzippori, once I was going in the upper marketplace of ציפורי. Tzippori.
ומצאתי אחד, umatzati echad, ויעקב איש כפר סכניא שמו. veYaakov ish Kfar
Sekanya shemo. Now this is a funny grammar. I found one person
and יעקב Yaakov the man of Sekanya was his name. It actually
of course is a expunged text and the original text reads: ומצאתי
אחד מתלמידיו של ישו הנוצרי, umatzati echad mitalmidav shel Yeshu HaNotzri, and
I found one of the students of ישו הנוצרי, Yeshu HaNotzri, and
his name was יעקב איש כפר סכניא, Yaakov ish Kfar Sekanya, so
we're talking clearly about the Christians. ואמר לי, ve'amar li, and he
said to me, כתוב בתורתכם, katuv betoratchem, it's written in your Torah,
לא תביא אתנן זונה, lo tavi etnan zonah, you can't bring an
אתנן זונה, etnan zonah, a gift of a prostitute to the house
of God. מה לעשות ממנו בית הכסא לכהן גדול? mah la'asot mimenu
beit hakisse lechohen gadol? Can you make from it a בית הכסא,
beit hakisse, an outhouse for the כהן גדול? kohen gadol? כהן גדול
Kohen Gadol has to live on the Temple Mount for the seven
days before
יום כיפור, Yom Kippur, so maybe you could make a toilet out
of something that was once a gift to a prostitute, maybe that
wouldn't be inappropriate? ולא אמרתי לו כלום, velo amarti lo klum, I
didn't respond to him. Now I didn't say like I don't know,
he said I didn't respond to him, you know, because sometimes they
say, right, the best way to deal with missionaries is you just
walk by. Don't try to engage them in argument, they love that,
it just draws you in. Okay. But anyway, אמר לי, amar li,
so but he didn't walk away. I didn't respond, but he didn't
walk away. אמר לי, amar li, and he said to me, כך
לימדני, kach limadani, here is what I was taught. And the original
version is כך לימדני ישו הנוצרי, kach limadani Yeshu HaNotzri, here is
what Jesus taught me. Okay. Now the dating is wrong, right, because
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer was the רבי Rebbe of רבי עקיבא, Rabbi
Akiva, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva was about 130. So somebody around 130...
maybe you could get it, that's true, no, maybe it's possible.
Jesus was around the year 30.
Yeah, I don't think you're getting a direct descendant of Jesus, a
direct student of Jesus, but anyway.
Like,
just on theory, רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is supposed to have died,
right, with the Bar Kochba revolt. Yeah.
So he died then. I thought no.
Yes, but that's the עשרה הרוגי מלכות. asarah harugei malchut. Okay.
I don't know, you probably know better than I do. All right,
maybe if this יעקב Yaakov guy is very old and whatever, I
don't know, maybe it's possible. It's roughly that context.
The one about יהושע בן פרחיה Yehoshua ben Perachia and Jesus.
I know, I know.
That didn't work out in terms of the timing.
Yeah, yeah.
So these emendated texts, like do you have?
Yeah, yeah, they were not in this version, but a lot of
the other versions restore it. Yeah. Okay. And it's in the manuscripts
and whatever, it's in the ראשונים. Rishonim. Okay. So anyway, I don't
know, sometimes these dates work out, sometimes they don't. You know, there's
a question how exactly historical this is. Anyway, he could just mean
that this is a religious teaching I have that originates from Jesus,
right? Not necessarily directly from Jesus. Anyway, כך לימדני, kach limadani, here
is what Jesus taught me. כי מאתנן זונה קבצה ועד אתנן זונה
ישובו, ki meetnan zonah kibtza ve'ad etnan zonah yashuvu, because it was
gathered from the payment of a prostitute and it will return to
the payment of a prostitute. ממקום הטינופת באו למקום הטינופת ילכו, mimmekom
hatinofet ba'u lemakom hatinofet yelechu,
it came from a place of filth and
will go to a place of filth. Okay. So then, what? ספריא
Sefaria goes with Steinzaltz.
Right, what? ספריא Sefaria takes Steinzaltz.
Yeah,
yeah.
Steinzaltz was not, I mean, Steinzaltz is all nice and good, but
they were not the only ones to restore the text. I'm just
saying, anyway, whatever, moving on. Okay. Anyway, והנאני
הדבר, vehenani hadavar,
and I said,
oh, that's a good חאפ. chap. You used this פסוק pasuk to
talk about, bring it, to apply it
to a
הלכה. halacha. as an actual matter of הלכה halacha it's פשוט pashut
that it was מותר muttar anyway because the whole הלכה halacha relates
to bringing it actually into the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash itself, not
just הר הבית, Har Habayis, but anyway, it doesn't matter that it
was an actual thing. He said like you know you actually got
some pleasure, oh a good חאפ, chap, you know? And then that
was why either G-d punished you because once you started enjoying it
you get pulled in and you know and we have to keep
our distance from it and that also could be why the Romans
suspected you. Okay.
על זה נתפסתי, Al zeh nitfasti, I mean this is why I
was seized and I was you know accused of this heresy. ועברתי
על מה שכתוב בתורה, Ve'avarti al mah shekasuv batorah, now he explains
it religiously. I transgressed what the תורה Torah said. הרחק מעליה דרכך,
Harcheik me'aleha darkecha, keep
far away from it your path, this is מינות. minut. ואל תקרב
אל פתח ביתה, Ve'al tikrav el pesach beisah,
and don't get close to the opening of the house, this is
the רשות, rashut, the government. He said which is obviously intertwined here
right? It's the government that seized me, the government is dangerous and
מינות minut is dangerous. Okay. ואיכא דאמרי Ve'ika de'amri and don't think
you'll get close and shammy with the government. ואיכא דאמרי Ve'ika de'amri
another say הרחק מעליה דרכך, Harcheik me'aleha darkecha, זו מינות ורשות, zo
minut verashut, that that is both heresy and the government. That's the
first part of the פסוק. pasuk. ואל תקרב אל פתח ביתה, Ve'al
tikrav el pesach beisah, do not get close to its house, זו
זונה, zo zonah, that is prostitution, right? Because that's actually the other
part of the thing that we mentioned, אתנן
זונה.
esnan zona.
וכמה, Vekamah, how distant you have to remain from a walk don't
walk by you know a house of prostitution don't walk by you
know a house of מינות, minut, how far away do you have
to keep your distance? אמר רב חסדא Amar Rav Chisda ארבע אמות,
arba amos, four אמות. amos. Now I want to stop and make
a point here which is about I'll make another point after we
finish you'll remind me but anyway which is that what would you
call it
that what would you have said if we had not just learned
this דף daf and I said we're learning מסכת עבודה זרה Masechet
Avodah Zarah and the גמרא Gemara quotes the פסוק pasuk הרחק מעליה
דרכך ואל תקרב אל פתח ביתה harcheik me'aleha darkecha ve'al tikrav el
pesach beisah about
keeping our distance from certain buildings. What would you imagine it would
want us to keep our distance from?
Well I mean I would think ביתה beisah I mean like the
בית beis of a of a עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
I am not asking you the פשט pshat of the פסוק. pasuk.
This verse is being used, we're learning מסכת עבודה זרה, Masechet Avodah
Zarah, what's the first thing you would think that it wants us
to keep our distance from?
עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah.
A house of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. So here the גמרא Gemara
quoted three things to keep away from and none of them were
עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, right? Which just speaks to how little idolatry
was a seduction and an attraction at the time of the חכמים.
Chachamim. Right? You have an entire tractate of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah
which is about keeping our distance, but you know, but in practice
and this is the point we made at the very beginning of
the מסכת masechet where it talks about like oh G-d's going to
take the ספר תורה Sefer Torah who was עוסק osek in תורה
מצוות Torah Mitzvos where the war wasn't with idolatry, the war was
keeping a life of תורה מצוות, Torah Mitzvos, right? And here the
seductions are the heresies, not עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, this paganism, this
idolatry, that's not interesting to me, right? You know, like the גמרא
Gemara says, by the time of בית שני Bayis Sheini the יצר
הרע yetzer hara of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah was no longer around,
you know, even for like a lot of the non-Jews it was
more like pro forma, you know, or whatever. Like Constantine right?
He went with the wind basicamente.
Well that's true but he was talking about Christianity, but that's right.
Anyway, so what was more so anyway so the seductions were getting
too involved in the I wouldn't say secular world but too involved
you know with the secular government getting you know oh power! You'll
be attracted by their power, right? Or you know the heresies that
you know all the different sectarians and the heresies and Christianity, that
was a powerful force not not עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah in the
sense of the idols, you know? And yeah, sexuality, the free sexuality
of the out of of of the larger world. So I think
this is like very powerful in identifying these are our threats nowadays,
not עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. Yes.
Did the חכמים Chachamim define what is עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah?
No, we've never exactly defined that, right?
Wouldn't it be fair to say that everything that is not what
we're doing is like some form...
So that's you know so that's true like nowadays right nowadays when
people get up like a rabbi gets up to talk about a
sermon he says our idolatry today is x you know is our
pursuit of materialism or our idolatry today is anything we give I
like the line anything which is true it's like a it's like
an abstraction anything that you give ultimate value to that's an idolatry
the only thing that has ultimate value is G-d. Okay but what
all that what that's doing is it's abstracting a very concrete reality
of idolatry which is no longer our issue and abstracting what it
means and applying it to something that is our issue. So you're
right so in that metaphoric sense you could say maybe the גמרא
Gemara sort of saying that these things are our idolatry yesterday but
I don't even see that being said. Like I don't see anywhere
in this trying to frame it as a type of עבודה זרה
בימינו, Avodah Zarah b'yameinu, right? But you know certainly you know that's
again a way we deal with the fact that we don't have
a live idea of idolatry today. Okay, so all right, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, והא רבנן האי מאתנן זונה מאי דרשי ביה, ve-ha rabbanan hai
me-esnan zonah mai darshi be, so the Rabbis, you know, as a
point as opposed to Jesus, the Rabbis, what do they explain this
verse about coming from a gift of a prostitute, coming from filth,
going to filth, what does how the Rabbis explain it? כדרב חסדא,
kedirav Chisda, like רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, דאמר רב חסדא, de-amar Rav
Chisda, כל זונה שנשכרת, kol zonah she-niskeres, any prostitute that hires herself
out for sex, לבסוף היא שוכרת, levasof hi socheres, in the end
she will like, you know, she'll lose her beauty and her attraction,
she'll fall on hard times, and since all she knows is like
this life, she'll actually use her money to have to hire people
to have sex with her, שנאמר, shene-emar, ובתתך אתנן ואתנן לא ניתן
לך ותהי להיפך, uvisiteich esnan ve-esnan lo nisan lach va-tehi le-hefech, you
know, in your giving of the אתנן esnan
and an אתנן esnan was not given to you, and it was
the reverse of what it used to be. Now you, the prostitute,
will have to give the fee and you're not no longer getting
your fee. Okay, ופליגי דרב פדת. u-pleigei de-rav Padat. Now this idea
of staying four אמות amos away disagrees with רב פדת. Rav Padat.
דאמר רב פדת, de-amar Rav Padat, לא אסרה תורה אלא קריבה של
גילוי עריות בלבד, lo asrah Torah ela kereivah shel gilluy arayos bilvad,
that when the תורה Torah says like לא תקרבו לגלות ערוה, lo
sikrevu legallos ervah, don't be close to having, you know, don't draw
close to reveal nakedness, it doesn't mean not physically being close to
like a house of prostitution. It means don't actually have an act
of forbidden intercourse. Okay, the תורה Torah only forbade actual intercourse, שנאמר
shene-emar as the verse says, איש איש אל כל שאר בשרו לא
תקרבו לגלות ערוה. ish ish el kol sheer besaro lo sikrevu legallos
ervah.
Okay,
now, the תוספות Tosafot says I don't understand what's bothering the גמרא
Gemara because, okay, biblically only an act of intercourse is forbidden, that
doesn't mean that the Rabbis can't say keep four אמות amos away.
Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says that well the point is that רב
פדת Rav Padat says the word לא תקרבו lo sikrevu does not
just mean real like, you know, does not just mean physical proximity.
And if it doesn't mean that in the verse here where it
means actual intercourse, so when it says לא תקרב אל פתח ביתה,
lo sikrav el pesach beisah, he presumably even rabbinically he wouldn't interpret
it to mean that you have to actually, you know, you can't
be physically proximate. Okay, רב פדת Rav Padat so therefore, anyway, so
רב פדת Rav Padat would not sort of, the way he explains
the scope of this verse or in general, he's not as worried
and therefore he would not say that you cannot have physical proximity.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this,
רמב"ן Ramban actually does an interesting רמב"ן, Ramban, it's a little ironic,
but רמב"ן Ramban says the phrase לא אסרה תורה lo asrah Torah
really means the Rabbis didn't forbid.
It sounds funny, but he means it means like,
you know, because the תורה Torah didn't forbid the Rabbis also didn't
forbid. So that how, you know, so that's like רב פדת Rav
Padat is so then he actually is even making a statement that
rabbinically we would not have forbid something about just physical proximity. Okay,
so now גמרא Gemara says like this, עולא כי
הוי אתי, Ulla ki havi ati, now we're going to digress a
little bit and talk about this question about is some form of
actual physical contact with people that are, you know, between a man
and a woman who's forbidden to him sexually, is
non-sexual physical contact forbidden? Okay, so עולא כי הוי אתי מבי רב,
Ulla ki havi ati mi-bei Rav, now עולא Ulla when he would
come back from his study house, הוי מנשק לאחתיה, havi menashak lachasei,
he'd come home and he'd kiss his sister אביידייהו abei yadaihu on
her hand, you know, like ספרדים Sefardim like still do that, right,
the hand. And then there's ואמרי לה אביי חדייהו, va-amrei lei abei
chadaihu, and some say on her chest. So that seems a little
weird, yeah. Okay, you don't know how old the sister was, you
know, you don't know anyway, presumably it was whatever, I mean, you
know, as far as these things have to do with like social
conventions. Anyway, ופליגי דידיה אדידיה. u-pleigei didei adidei. Now the fact that
he felt that that type of non-sexual touch was permissible, he argues
on himself. דאמר עולא, de-amar Ulla, because עולא Ulla says קריבה בעלמא
אסור, kereivah be-alma asur, any type of physical contact is forbidden,
משום לך לך אמרינן לנזירא, mishum lech lech amrinan lenezira, because go
away, go away, we say to the נזירא, nezira, like not like
the Jesuan Nazarene, the נזירא, nezira, סחור סחור לכרמא לא תקרב, sechor
sechor lecharma lo sikrav, don't even get close to the vineyard. So
therefore,
the idea that we have what do you call
it? That we just have that we have to keep a distance,
that we have these safeguards. Now this is a very I'll just
speak for a second about this. So why is it that the
other עולא, Ulla, meaning forget how to reconcile them, but how do
you explain why he felt it was okay to like kiss his
sister's hand or whatever? So if you look at תוספות, Tosafot, תוספות
Tosafot says ופליגי דידיה אדידיה, u-pleigei didei adidei, if you look at
תוספות, Tosafot, the second ופליגי, u-pleigei, ומה שהיה מיקל בעצמו היינו משום
דדמיין עליה כי כשורא. u-mah shehayah meikel atzmo haynu mishum dedamyan alei
ki kishura. The fact that he was lenient was because he didn't
get any sexual charge from it that was really, you know, it
didn't lead to him having sexual thoughts or anything of that nature.
There was no sexual overtones. So here becomes an important question about
is there actually any often
the normal story you hear is that rabbinically any form of physical
contact contact even neutral is rabbinically forbidden between let's say a man
and a woman that's married to another man or a נדה Niddah
whatever the case might be you know and however you know the
whole discussion had shaking hands at work well you know if it's
an issue of כבוד הבריות Kevod HaBriyot you know then you're like
allowed so therefore if the other person sticks out their hand you
can take out your hand and then the question do you stick
out your hand first you know whatever anyway that's like how the
normal conversation goes. But the real point is that according to many
many ראשונים Rishonim there is no rabbinic prohibition against neutral touch. The
only prohibition is around sexual touch. And the fact that עולא Ula
you know went ahead and did this shows that there's no formal
prohibition. What it means is that if a man or a woman
feels that even in casual touch that there will be some sexual
charge then they shouldn't have that then they shouldn't you know have
that type of touch. But if the touch will be totally neutral
then there's actually like no formal prohibition. So it's not that like
oh you can shake hands because you need a מתיר matir of
כבוד הבריות. Kevod HaBriyot. Like fundamentally I think it makes a real
difference about how we think about this to say like fundamentally you
know the rabbis never forbade neutral touch but if there's a concern
that it'll be more than neutral touch even like an undertone of
that or whatever then that's something that you should not do and
avoid.
So that's the לך לך lech lech part.
Meaning if it's touch that's going to... the לך לך lech lech
is like if you're concerned that it might be a little bit
more than something neutral you
know whatever then keep away. But if you know that it'll just
be neutral touch no problem. And it's very different than the normal
way in which you hear that being told of just a מתיר
matir of כבוד הבריות. Kevod HaBriyot. Anyway so but I do want
to say one final thing though which is that exactly which is
and we're not going to give a whole שיעור shiur about this
but the last thing to mention is is that
the פסוק pasuk that was quoted איש איש אל כל שאר בשרו
ish ish el kol she'er besaro שאר בשרו she'er besaro specifically means
relatives right? So therefore that so there's actually two well three categories
of of like you know of relations of like forbidden acts of
sex. One is between relatives you know close relatives. One is between
a man and a married woman and one is between a man
and his wife who is a נדה. Niddah. So let's put the
נדה Niddah thing aside. So the question is is there a difference
between the issue about relatives and the issue about a married woman?
You know so we might obviously want to allow more touch between
a brother and a sister than we would allow between a man
and a woman who is married to another man. You know both
because we assume that the touch between brother and sister you know
is more likely a we might not want to restrict it they
have family ties you know we might sort of think that there's
positive value in allowing it. We we can presume that maybe it
will be less likely to be sexual. You know and also if
a man for us we would say even if the man is
married to another woman or the woman is married to another man
you know they're the other parties involved and they might you know
be even if the two you know they might sort of feel
like a sense of of inappropriateness or whatever there's other things to
consider. So anyway רמב"ן Ramban definitely definitely says that part of this
whole discussion is specifically in the context of like brothers and sisters
and you know relatives etc. and it might be you know might
be more restrictive in the context of a man and a married
woman. So that's an interesting question about that. Okay so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this...
so it means that there's less meaning there's more room to be
מיקל mekel for family...
yes
and the fact that עולא Ula here was with his sister doesn't
necessarily translate into the same thing about a man and a married
woman. Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: what are you saying though that he's saying קורץ קורץ korts
korts that that he's saying that even with...
well it's not clear
in cases where that's a concern or maybe he's talking about a
non-relative place. Okay going on.
עלוקה שתי בנות Alukah shtei banot to the עלוקה Alukah which is
some type of a I don't know just what how do they
translate it? I looked this up before.
Didn't we have עלוקה Alukah means a leech before? A leech? Well
what? A leech but as they said it's referring to...
I know. Okay but that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to
interpret. Okay to the leech has two daughters הב הב hav hav
and they say give give. So מאי הב הב? mai hav hav?
What is give give? So אמר מר עוקבא amar Mar Ukva כל
שתי בנות שצועקות מגהינום kol shtei banot shetzo'akot migehinnom it's the two
daughters that are crying out from גהינום gehinnom ואומרת בעולם הזה הב
הב ve'omeret ba'olam hazeh hav hav
and says in this world give give meaning these are the things
that are seducing you in this world and are bringing you down
to גהינום. gehinnom. ומן נינהו? Uman ninhu? And what are they? מינות
ורשות. Minut verashut. They are you know heresy and the...
the two daughters are מינות Minut and רשות? Rashut?
Yes the two daughters are the two things that are seducing you
into גהינום gehinnom that seem very attractive in this world you know
are heresy that's intellectually seductive and attractive and the and the government
which is attractive because of its power. איכא דאמרי Ika de'amri others
say אמר רב חסדא אמר מר עוקבא amar Rav Chisda amar Mar
Ukva כל גהינום צועקת ואומרת הבי לי שתי בנות שצועקות ואומרת בעולם
הזה הב הב הב הב הב הב. kol gehinnom tzo'akat ve'omeret havi
li shtei banot shetzo'akot ve'omeret ba'olam hazeh hav hav hav hav hav
hav.
Okay anyway so others say a different version of this that the
sound from גהינום gehinnom is crying out and says give me my
two daughters who cry out in this world. and say give give.
Okay. כל באיה לא ישובון ולא ישיגו ארחות חיים Kol ba-eha lo
yeshuvun v'lo yasigu orchot chayim all those who go down there will
not return and they will never find the path of life. So
this going down means like follow after heresy. Okay is how it's
being understood.
You missed that book by Shulem Deen, All
Who Go Do Not Return. There you go, there you go. Okay
so all those who follow after heresy will not return. Okay guys
we just need to focus. וכי מאחר דלא שבו היכן ישיגו? V'chi
me'achar d'lo shavu heichan yasigu? So I don't get it, if they
won't return how of course they won't achieve the path of life,
they'll stay trapped in their heresy. הכי קאמר, Hachi ka'amar, here's what
it means: ואי שבו v'ee shavu if they try to return, לא
ישיגו ארחות חיים lo yasigu orchot chayim then they won't be able
to, it'll be so difficult to leave that world of heresy that
if they try to return, it'll kill them. Okay, למימרא, L'meimra, so
the Gemara says, does that mean to say דכל דפריש ממינות מאית,
d'kol d'parish mi-minus meit, anybody who separates from heresy will as a
result of that, you know, sort of like
spiritual difficulty trying to strip away his נשמה neshama as it was
caught up in all that stuff, that the cost is death? והא
ההיא דאתא לקמיה דרב חסדא, Ve-ha hahi d'ata l'kamei d'Rav Chisda, a
woman came in front of רב חסדא Rav Chisda and said to
him,
ואמרה ליה, v'amra leh, קלה שבקלות עשתה בנה קטן מבנה גדול. kala
she-bi-kalot asta b'na katan mi-b'na gadol. She said the lightest sin that
I've done, I am such a sinner, the lightest sin I've done
is my youngest son was born from my oldest son, meaning that
I had intercourse with my older son and through that I had
my... that's one of the light sins that I've done. Okay,
and רב חסדא Rav Chisda said to her, ואמר לה רב חסדא,
v'amar la Rav Chisda, טרחו לה בזוודתא. tarchu la b'zavdeta. You know,
go start preparing for her
her shrouds, the things that are going to accompany her in her
burial, okay, because now she's going to die. She's trying, she was
trying to do תשובה, teshuva, she told him this is one of
my light sins, he said oh my god it's going to be
so hard for you to do תשובה teshuva in this process you're
probably going to die. Okay,
and what happened? ולא מיתה, v'lo meita, in the end she didn't
die. So now why is that a question? מדקאמרה קלה שבקלות עשתה,
mide-ka-amra kala she-bi-kalot asta, since she said that was my lightest
sin, מכלל, m'chlal, so that means everything, she did everything that was
like worse than that. So that obviously includes heresy. Okay, obviously in
the way that we're sort of saying heresy is worse than
having sex with your son and having a son from... anyway, מכלל
דמינות נמי הויא בה, m'chlal d'minus nami hava bah, she also had
heresy and she did תשובה teshuva and she didn't die. So how
could that be if you say everybody who leaves heresy dies? So
no, ההיא דלא הדרה בה שפיר, Hahi d'lo hadra bah shapir, no,
she didn't do real תשובה. teshuva. ומשום הכי לא מיתה, U-mishum hachi
lo meita, that's why she survived because she didn't really totally extract
herself. If you totally extract yourself you would have died in the
process. Right. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amrei, others say, ממינות אין מעבירה לא,
mi-minus in me-aveira lo, so this only from heresy when you try
to separate yourself from it you die, מעבירה me-aveira no, not from
other
sins.
והא ההיא דאתא לקמיה דרב חסדא ואמר ליה
רב חסדא זודו לה זוודתא, Ve-ha hahi d'ata l'kamei d'Rav Chisda v'amar
leh Rav Chisda zudu la zavdeta, but how about this whole story
about this woman? ומתה, U-meita, and in this version of the story
she did die. Now why did she die if she only had
other sins, she didn't have heresy? So the Gemara says no, מדקאמרה
קלה שבקלות, mide-ka-amra kala she-bi-kalot, she did have heresy. Since she said
that was her lightest sin, מכלל דמינות נמי הויא בה, m'chlal d'minus
nami hava bah, she also had heresy. Okay so according to one
version she also was involved in heresy and she died as a
result of תשובה, teshuva, and according to the other version she did
not die because she didn't do real תשובה. teshuva. Fine. But really
it's heresy that leaving it causes you to die and not the
other say. Okay, so now the Gemara says like
this: ומעבירה לא? U-me-aveira lo? When you try to separate from other
sin or maybe specifically sexual sin, are you telling me that won't
cause you to die? והתניא, Ve-hatanya, this is a famous story. If
anybody's ever heard any rabbinic story I bet you've heard this one.
והתניא אמרו עליו על אלעזר בן דורדיא, Ve-hatanya amru alav al Elazar
ben Durdaya, they said about אלעזר בן דורדיא Elazar ben Durdaya שלא
הניח זונה אחת בעולם שלא בא עליה, she-lo hiniach zona achat ba-olam
she-lo ba aleha, that he did not leave one זונה, zona, one
prostitute in the entire world that he did not have intercourse with.
פעם אחת שמע שיש זונה אחת בכרכי הים, Pa'am achat shama she-yesh
zona achat b'charchei ha-yam, once he heard that there was a prostitute
that lived in some island overseas, והיתה נוטלת כיס דינרים בשכרה, v'haita
notelt kis dinarim bi-schara, and she her fee was very high, it
was an entire
wallet filled of דינרי, dinarei, of gold דינרי. dinarei. נטל כיס דינרים,
Natal kis dinarim, he took a wallet filled with hundreds, okay, והלך
ועבר עליה שבעה נהרות, v'halach v'avar aleha shiva neharot, crossed seven
rivers. בשעת הרגל דבר, B'shat hergel davar, at the time when they
were involved in the matter, when they're actually having intercourse or getting
ready to have intercourse, הפיחה, heficha, she either blew out or she
like, you know, with her mouth or she passed wind, okay, ואמרה,
v'amra, and she said, כשם שהפיחה זו אינה חוזרת למקומה כך אלעזר
בן דורדיא אין מקבלין אותו בתשובה. k'shem she-heficha zu eina chozeret li-m'koma
kach Elazar ben Durdaya ein mikablin oto bi-tshuva. The same way this
wind that I just or breath that I just released is not
going to come back into me,
so אלעזר בן דורדיא Elazar ben Durdaya you've given up your soul,
you will never be able to return in תשובה. teshuva. Now I
don't know why what led this prostitute to all of a sudden
care about this man's righteousness and to say this thing to him,
that's never explained. Anyway.
And then she comes and she marries the guy, she's מגייר *megayer*,
no it's תשובה teshuvah, *teshuva*, she's מגייר *megayer*. Anyway, here she's not
מגייר *megayer*. Anyway, okay, so he now this woke him up. Okay,
הלך וישב בין שני הרים וגבעות *Halach veyashav bein shenei harim ugvaot*.
He sat between these two major, two mountains. אמר הרים וגבעות *Amar
harim ugvaot*, mountains and you know hills, בקשו עלי רחמים *bikshu alai
rachamim*, pray for me to help me do תשובה teshuvah, *teshuva*. אמרו
לו amru lo, *Amru lo*, עד שאנו מבקשים עליך נבקש על עצמנו
*ad she'anu mevakshim alecha nevakesh al atzmenu*. We have to worry about
ourselves, שנאמר כי ההרים ימושו והגבעות תמוטנה *shene'emar ki heharim yamushu vehagvaot
temutena*. The mountains will be removed and the hills will be, you
know, will be uprooted. So
we, you know, our own survival is not sure. We have to
pray for ourselves. אמר שמים וארץ בקשו עלי רחמים *Amar shamayim va'aretz
bikshu alai rachamim*, heaven and earth. אמרו amru, לו עד שאנו מבקשים
עליך נבקש על עצמנו *Amru lo ad she'anu mevakshim alecha nevakesh al
atzmenu*. You want us to pray for you? We have to worry
about ourselves. שנאמר כי שמים כעשן נמלחו והארץ כבגד תבלה *shene'emar ki
shamayim ke'ashan nimlachu veha'aretz kevaged tivale*.
The heavens will be, you know, blow away like the smoke and
the world will, you know, wear away like a garment. So we're
also impermanent and we have to worry about ourselves. אמר חמה ולבנה
בקשו עלי רחמים *Amar chama ulevana bikshu alai rachamim*, sun and moon.
אמרו לו עד שאנו מבקשים עליך נבקש על עצמנו *Amru lo ad
she'anu mevakshim alecha nevakesh al atzmenu*. We have to worry about ourselves.
שנאמר וחפרה הלבנה ובושה החמה *shene'emar vechafra halevana uvoshah hachama*. The sun
will be, the moon will be embarrassed and the sun will be
shamed. אמר כוכבים ומזלות בקשו עלי רחמים *Amar kochavim umazalot bikshu alai
rachamim*, stars. אמרו לו עד שאנו מבקשים עליך נבקש על עצמנו *Amru
lo ad she'anu mevakshim alecha nevakesh al atzmenu*. We have to worry
about ourselves. שנאמר ונמקו כל צבא השמים *shene'emar venamaku kol tzeva hashamayim*.
All of the host of the heaven will melt away. אמר אין
הדבר תלוי אלא בי *Amar ain hadavar talui ela bi*. Oh, the
only, it's all up to me. I have to find the strength
within myself. Right? הניח ראשו בין ברכיו *Hiniach rosho bein birkav*. He
put his head between his knees, וגעה בבכיה *vagaa bivchiya*. It's interesting,
like the image of the head between the knees sort of evoke
him sitting between the mountains, you know, if you think about like
when you have your knees up or whatever, you know, it's sort
of similar, right? So the, you see the image? The person between
the mountain, the head between the knees.
Anyway, reborn in a way.
What?
Head between... oh, that's interesting, like the fetus, like a birth. Oh,
that's interesting. Okay. And he said, וגעה בבכיה *vagaa bivchiya*, he let
out in cry, עד שיצתה נשמתו *ad sheyatzta nishmato*, until his soul
departed him. יצתה בת קול Bat Kol *Yatzta bas kol*. So his
נשמה *neshama* departed him, and remember that was like the blowing out
that the prostitute did, right? So the spirit departed, and then יצתה
בת קול *yatzta bas kol*, then the בת קול *bas kol* came
out, ואמרה *ve'amrah*, רבי אלעזר בן דורדיא Rabbi Eliezer Ben Durdaya. מזומן
לחיי העולם הבא *Rebbi Elazar ben Durdia mezuman lechayei ha'olam haba*. He
is, you know, on his way to עולם הבא Olam HaBa, *Olam
Haba*. I always wondered about the phrase מזומן לחיי העולם הבא *mezuman
lechayei ha'olam haba*. Why doesn't it say he's going to get עולם
הבא Olam HaBa *Olam Haba*? מזומן *mezuman* or he, you know, מזומן
*mezuman* somehow sounds like it's a preparation, he's prepared for it, but
he's not necessarily there yet. I don't know, maybe he still had
to get punished in גיהנום *Gehennom* before he could get into עולם
הבא Olam HaBa, *Olam Haba*. I don't know. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, והא *veha*... so the whole purpose of this
wonderful powerful story is to get to the question. והא בעבירה הוה
ומית *Veha ba'aveira hava umit*? This was sexual sin and he died
as a result of trying to depart from it? התם נמי כיון
דאדבק בה תשובה כמינות דמיא *Hatam nami keivan deadbak bah teshuva keminut
damya*. No. Somebody who really immerses themselves in it, that's like, that
becomes their, like, there you go, here, now here you are, Michal,
that becomes their עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah, *avoda zara*. although it doesn't
say it becomes their עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah. *avoda zara*. It says
it becomes their מינות minut, *minut*, heresy. Okay, but the point is
that it gets so intertwined with your soul, it's not just something
external. I do these acts and they're sinful acts, it so much
gets into your mind or into your heart or into your essence,
that to try to transform yourself and get out of that, the
גמרא gemara *Gemara* is saying, actually causes you to die. Now, I
want to say some points about this,
about the mountains and the, about the mountains etc., what's the whole
point about that thing? So the מהרש"א maharsha *Maharsha* says that the
point is is that he knew, he was afraid that he was
going to die as a result because of what we've been saying,
so basically he's looking to the heavens and the stars for help
because he doesn't want to die, and what they're telling him is
is like, you know what, it's not the worst thing in the
world to die. The entire world is transitory. The world is going
to go away. There are things that are more important. You should
be allowed, don't feel like you have to remain permanent and anchored
in this world. Like, you know, do what is necessary in terms
of your spirit and don't worry about that. So that's how he
reads that their response had to do with sort of the transitory
nature of the world. You know, I also think that there's a,
in my mind, and this just could be because we're learning מסכת
עבודה זרה *Masechet Avoda Zara*, there could be an echo of the
earlier מדרש Midrash, *Midrash* that we did way back on דף ג'
*daf gimmel*, which was about the שמים *shamayim* and the ארץ *aretz*
come to testify that the Jews kept the תורה Torah *Torah*. And
it said there that... and do you remember why they were treated
as פסול *pasul* witnesses? Why the non-Jews said "Oh, they're invalid as
witnesses"? Because they said they're נוגע בדבר *nogeia badavar*. You know why
they're נוגע בדבר *nogeia badavar*? Because if the Jews don't keep the
תורה Torah *Torah*, then they're gonna all... then the heavens and earth
will all disappear. The existence of the heaven and earth are dependent
on the Jews keeping the תורה Torah *Torah*. So here the heavens
and the earth and the mountains are saying, "We have to pray
for ourselves because of your sin." That's the way I'm reading it.
"Your sin, you're worried, you want us to help you? Your sin..."
you know, when people sin that threatens the very foundations of creation.
So we have to worry now about ourselves, you know? So it's
like, which is like a pretty harsh, like now it's not just
enough that he's sinned himself, now he's threatening the existence of the...
but I do wonder if that's like a possible echo, you know,
here about like about what's about what's going on, yeah.
The other point that becomes a little bit ironic, right? Like the
genius of עבודה זרה, well this isn't עבודה זרה, but you're praying
to things that are not God, you're praying to the mountains.
That's an interesting point too, right?
In in you know, as far as I knew, don't at least
הגר"א, the Gra, right, מכניסי רחמים, Machnisei Rachamim, and...
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
He, but here, he, you know, it seems okay. I mean, I
don't know what to make.
Right, it's a good point, that's an excellent point in terms of
thinking about the issues that come around, you know, of like attitudes
around like when you say ברכוני לשלום Barchuni L'shalom by מלאכי השרת,
Malachei HaShareit, by מכניסי רחמים, Machnisei Rachamim, do you pray to or
request, not pray, request from other entities to intercede for God on
your behalf? And here he certainly like was doing that. So that's
a very good point too, in the context of עבודה זרה. All
right, let's keep on going. Okay, so now בכה רבי ואמר. Bakha
Rabbi V'amar.
Now רבי Rabbi cried and said, יש קונה עולמו בכמה שנים ויש
קונה עולמו בשעה אחת. Yesh Koneh Olomo B'khama Shanim V'yesh Koneh Olomo
B'shaa Akhat. Some people they spend their entire life trying to get
עולם הבא, and some get it in one minute. ואמר רבי V'amar
Rabbi and רבי, Rabbi, you know, so he sort of said like,
you know, it's very beautiful that this person was able to do
תשובה, but like where's the justice? I'm spending my whole life devoting
to תורה ומצוות, Torah and Mitzvot, you know, ואמר רבי, V'amar Rabbi,
so you know, but part of the answer to that is and
since when is the whole purpose of your life whether you're going
to get עולם הבא or not? I mean רבי Rabbi is living
a life that's much more purposeful than this person's life, but anyway.
ואמר רבי V'amar Rabbi and רבי Rabbi said, לא דיין לבעלי תשובה
שמקבלין אותן, Lo Dayan L'ba'alei Teshuvah She'mekablin Otan, if for בעלי תשובה
Ba'alei Teshuvah it's not enough that they get received in the world
to come if they do תשובה, אלא שקורין אותן רבי, Ella She'korin
Otam Rabbi, they get called רבי, Rabbi, because it said רבי, Rabbi,
you know, what would the בת קול say? רבי Rabbi, אלעזר בן
דורדיא. Who gave him סמיכה? semikhah? All right. So it's it's not
fair! Like okay, he gets עולם הבא, he gets called to be
a
רבי, okay. רבי חנינא ורבי יונתן הוו קאזלי באורחא. Rabbi Chanina V'rabbi
Yonatan Havai Ka'azli B'orkha. Now back to this idea. So all of
this obviously shows the tremendous seduction of
idolatry of of heresy, not idolatry, of heresy, of power, of the
government, and of sexual freedom. So
רבי חנינא ורבי יונתן הוו קאזלי באורחא, Rabbi Chanina V'rabbi Yonatan Havai
Ka'azli B'orkha, they were on the way. מטו להנך תרי שבילי, Matu
L'hanei Trei Shvilei, they came to the inevitable crossroads in the path.
They came to the crossroads, two paths. And as we all know
Yogi Berra says, when you come to a fork in the road,
take it. So they had to decide how to take it, okay?
So חד פטיא אפיתחא דעבודת כוכבים, Chad Patya A'pitcha D'avodas Kokhavim, one
went by the house of עבודת כוכבים, Avodas Kokhavim, וחד פטיא אפיתחא
דבי זונות, V'chad Patya A'pitcha D'bei Zonot, and the other went by
the house of prostitution. אמר ליה חד לחבריה ניזיל אפיתחא דעבודת כוכבים.
Amar Lei Chad L'chavrei Neizel A'pitcha D'avodas Kokhavim. Now if my point
earlier was only implicit, here it's explicit. Let's go by the house
that goes by עבודת כוכבים, Avodas Kokhavim, דנחייס יצריה, D'nakhis Yitrei,
because the יצר הרע Yetzer Hara עבודת כוכבים Avodas Kokhavim has already
been slaughtered. We have no יצר הרע, Yetzer Hara, what's the big
deal walking by a house of עבודת כוכבים? Avodas Kokhavim? It's not
seductive. So the גמרא Gemara is saying it black and white, this
is not where our seductions lie in this world. אמר ליה אידך,
Amar Lei Idakh, the other one said, no, ניזיל אפיתחא דבי זונות,
Neizel A'pitcha D'bei Zonot, let's go by the house of prostitution, ונכפייה
ליצרן. V'nikhpyeih L'yitran.
Let's actually, you know, do it to give ourselves a נסיון. nisayon.
You know, we'll we will we will be we'll feel the sort
of, you know, the urge, we'll feel the seduction, and we'll keep
on the straight and narrow. All right, we'll keep on the straight
and narrow, you know, it's a very it's a very also good
image, right? It's like the seductions that are leading you off of
the near, you know, of the straight and narrow, of the right
path, okay? And we will we will subjugate our desire, ונקבל אגרא,
V'nekabel Igra, and we'll receive reward. So they did that. כי מטו
התם, Ki Matu Hatam, when they got there, חזינהו לזונות, Chazinu L'zonot,
they saw the prostitutes, איסתקנו מקמייהו, Iskanu Mikamaya,
and rather than them being seduced by the prostitutes, the prostitutes were
embarrassed and they all went into they they you know, rather than
plying their trade on the on the road, they all went into
the house. Okay, they they they hid. אמר ליה מנא לך הא,
Amar Lei Minalakh Ha,
so he said to him, whoever it was the one who said,
the anyway, one said to the other, where do you get this
idea from? How did you know that it was okay we could
go by this house and not be seduced and so on? So
אמר ליה מזימה תשמור עליך, Amar Lei Mizimah Tishmor Alekha,
the תורה Torah will protect you from from what's
it from promiscuity, okay? From improper sexuality. תבונה תנצרך, Tvunah Tintzarekha, the
the wisdom understanding will protect you. Okay, so yes, obviously we're told
you're not supposed to put yourself to a נסיון nisayon and that's
just asking for trouble. Anyway, which here they were here they felt
they could do it, and he believed that the תורה Torah, would
protect him and lo and behold the תורה Torah did protect him.
So once again, right, it is what protects us from the outside
world? The life of תורה ומצוות Torah and Mitzvot and more specifically
תורה Torah? like God with the ספר תורה Sefer Torah in in
God's chest, the early מדרש, right? It's all very much the themes.
This is what keeps us in the world that we believe in
and protects us from the seductions of the outside world. אמרו ליה
רבנן לרבא, Amru Lei Rabbanan L'rava, so the rabbis said to רבא,
Rava,
I think it's important that they were not... it wasn't one person
alone.
Oh, so they were, that's a good point, but they were two
of them, so that actually also helped keep the other one on
the straight and narrow. That's a good point. אמרו ליה רבנן לרבא,
Amru lay Rabbanan LeRava, so the rabbi said to רבא, Rava, מהי
מזימה, mahi mezima, what does it mean מזימה? mezima? סלקא דעתך תורה,
salka datach Torah, maybe the word מזימה mezima means תורה, Torah. meaning
it's not from, from forbidden sex, or you know, from like promiscuity,
what it means is the תורה Torah. will protect you. Now how
would the word מזימה mezima mean תורה? Torah דכתיב מזימה, dechtiv mezima,
because the word מזימה mezima actually is a word that can be
used to refer to, to sort of, to תורה. Torah How do
we say that? ומתרגמינן עצה חכמתא, umatargaminan etza chochmata, because sometimes, because
the word מזימה mezima sometimes translated as the, the counsel or the,
the, what's the word עצה, etza, the, not the advice, yeah advice
or
whatever the, anyway, the counsel of the wicked. So מזימה mezima could
mean like counsel. So maybe מזימה mezima could mean like the wisdom
of the תורה. Torah דכתיב הפליא עצה הגדיל תושיה, dechtiv hifli etza
higdil tushia, you know, the advice was astounding, the, you know, great
was the salvation. So anyway, so maybe מזימה mezima means the תורה
Torah, will protect you. מזימה mezima maybe means planning, advice, understanding. אי
הכי זמה מיבעי ליה, ei hachi zima mibaei lay, it should have
said זמה, zima, if that's what we're going to translate. Not the
word מזימה. mezima. So anyway, אלא הכי קאמר, ela hachi ka-amar, מדבר
זמה תשמר לך, midevar zima tishmor lach, no what it means is,
and this is how we were interpreting it before, from a matter
of promiscuity the תורה Torah, will protect you. תורה תנצרכה, Torah tintzrecha,
the תורה Torah will protect you. Okay.
תנו רבנן. tanu rabbanan. So that was the end of that whole
story about being נתפס למינות, nitpas leminut, which was connected to the
idea of the guardrail and as a result we've explored the idea
that מינות, the government, and sexuality, were and you know free sex
or whatever were these real seductions of the outside world. Now we
have another story of two other great rabbis that are being seized
and judged by the Roman government. תנו רבנן, tanu rabbanan, we're just
going to get a little bit further here. כשנתפס רבי אלעזר בן
פרטא ורבי חנניא בן תרדיון. keshenitpas Rabbi Elazar ben Prata veRabbi Chananya
ben Teradyon. Rabbi Elazar ben Prata and Rabbi Elazar ben Teradyon were
seized and here it was not for suspicion of heresy, it was
for, you know, being involved in תורה, Torah this is like the
Hadrianic persecutions. Okay. אמר לו רבי אלעזר בן פרטא לרבי חנניא בן
תרדיון, amar lo Rabbi Elazar ben Prata leRabbi Chananya ben Teradyon, אשריך
שנתפסת על דבר אחד. ashreicha shenitpasta al davar echad. So Rabbi Elazar
says to Rabbi Chananya, praise are you that you have only, there's
only one charge against you.
אוי לי שנתפסתי על חמשה דברים, oy li shenitpasti al chamisha devarim,
woe to me I have five charges against me. How am I
ever going to get free of them? אמר לו רבי חנניא אשריך
שנתפסת על חמשה דברים ואתה ניצול. amar lo Rabbi Chananya ashreicha shenitpasta
al chamisha devarim ve-ata nitzol. So Rabbi Chananya somehow had some, you
know, some sense of what was to come and he said, no,
praise are you, you were, you've been seized about five things but
you will, you'll come out of it. You're not going to actually
be executed. You know, sometimes it's כל המוסיף גורע, kol hamosif goreia,
you have to come up with five charges, probably none of them
is a good one. Okay. אוי לי שנתפסתי על דבר אחד ואיני
ניצול, oy li shenitpasti al davar echad ve-eini nitzol, and I only
have one charge against me and it's a
biggie and I'm not going to be saved. שאתה עסקת בתורה ובגמילות
חסדים, she-ata asakta baTorah uvigmilut chasadim, and here's his religious explanation for
it. Why do you merit being saved? Because you did not just
devote yourself to תורה, Torah you devoted yourself to תורה Torah and
to kind deeds and to, you know, acts of kindness and helping
people. ואני לא עסקתי אלא בתורה בלבד, va-ani lo asakti ela baTorah
bilvad, and I just involved myself in תורה Torah and therefore I
do not have as much merit as you. Very powerful statement, somebody
who stays in ישיבה yeshiva and just learns and doesn't translate that
into a life of action is, you know, not as meritorious. וכדרב
הונא, uchederev Huna, like Rav Huna, דאמר רב הונא, da-amar Rav Huna,
כל העוסק בתורה בלבד, kol ha-osek baTorah bilvad, if anybody only learns
תורה Torah with the exclusion of translating that into deeds of kindness
and helping people, דומה כמי שאין לו אלוה. domeh kemi she-ein lo
elo-ah. It's like you don't have a God. Or you know here
by the way Michal if you wanted to use your metaphor before,
so there תורה Torah becomes their God. You know, yeah, their תורה
Torah, becomes their God and they right, you know,
exactly, exactly. If you really, if all of this was in service
of God then you would realize, you know, in the way the
מהרש"א says it, you're supposed to be like God. Well guess what,
God is גומל חסדים, gomel chasadim, God is
מנחם אבלים. menachem avelim. If you're, if this was not just about
your dedication to תורה Torah. but your dedication to God, it would
translate into other ways of acting and of living. Very powerful statement.
שנאמר וימים רבים לישראל ללא אלהי אמת. shene-emar veyamim rabbim leYisrael lelo
elohei emet. Many days in Israel that they did not have a
true God. מאי ללא אלהי אמת? mai lelo elohei emet? What do
you mean not a true God? And again, we would normally assume
that means like idolatry, right? So here you go using this like
re-shaping what the idea of idolatry's about. שכל העוסק בתורה בלבד דומה
כמי שאין לו אלוה. shekol ha-osek baTorah bilvad domeh kemi she-ein lo
elo-ah. That then you don't have a God, then תורה Torah, is
your God. Okay. Now the גמרא Gemara says one minute. ובגמילות חסדים
לא עסק? uvigmilut chasadim lo asak? Are you telling me that Rabbi
Chanina did not involve himself in
גמילות חסדים? gmilut chasadim? והתניא רבי אלעזר בן יעקב אומר, vehatanya Rabbi
Elazar ben Yaakov omer, לא
יתן אדם מעותיו לארנקי של צדקה, lo yitein adam me-otav le-arnaki shel
tzedaka, don't give your money to the wallet of צדקה, tzedaka, you
know to a צדקה tzedaka fund, אלא אם כן ממונה עליו תלמיד
חכם כרבי חנניא בן תרדיון, ela im kein memuneh alav talmid chacham
keRabbi Chananya ben Teradyon, unless you have somebody like a great sage
like Rabbi Chananya ben Teradyon. So I'm sure using him as an
example of somebody who could be trusted with צדקה tzedaka money, so.
Presumably, he involved himself in the world of collecting and distributing צדקה.
tzedakah. So what do you mean he didn't involve himself in that?
So the גמרא Gemara says no, הימנוהו הוא דהוה מהימן, himnuha hu
dehavei meheiman, he could be trusted, but מעבד לא עבד, ma'avad lo
avad, but he didn't actually, maybe it means he didn't actually give
his own money to צדקה, tzedakah, maybe it means that they were
just using him as a metaphor like if somebody could be trusted
like רבי חנניה בן תרדיון, Rabbi Chananya ben Teradyon, not like רבי
חנניה בן תרדיון Rabbi Chananya ben Teradyon actually was involved in this
profession, but he's an example of someone who could be trusted. So
the גמרא Gemara says, what do you mean? התניא, Hatanya, but we
taught, אמר לו, amar lo, once
רבי חנניה בן תרדיון Rabbi Chananya ben Teradyon said, 'מעות של פורים
נתחלפו לי במעות צדקה, ma'os shel Purim nitchalfu li b'ma'os tzedakah, I
accidentally exchanged some Purim money with tzedakah money, וחילקתים לעניים, v'chilaktim l'aniyim,
and I distributed to the poor.' So there's a whole question what
רש"י, Rashi, תוספות, Tosafot, what this means, but the short version of
it is that somehow I used the wrong money to give to
the poor, I gave them money that was collected for פורים Purim
and whatever, and I had to make up the money from the
צדקה tzedakah fund and I made it up out of my own
pocket. Okay, so clearly he was involved in giving צדקה tzedakah and
distributing צדקה, tzedakah, even in giving his own money to צדקה. tzedakah.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, מעבד עבד, ma'avad avad, fine, he
gave צדקה. tzedakah. כדבעי ליה לא עבד, k'debayei lei lo avad, he
didn't do what he really could have done. So now it's really
tough. Here's somebody who didn't just live in the ישיבה. Yeshiva. Of
course he did some acts of גמילות חסדים. gemilus chasadim. But you
know there's like doing it a little bit. And now it's not
just such a little bit, he's sticking his hand into his own
pocket, he's investing time in overseeing a צדקה tzedakah fund. So it's
like you know it's hard to say, 'Oh but he really could
have done more.' Because you know sometimes if somebody's really devoted to
תורה, Torah you think like okay look, I devote three hours a
week to this you know and the rest I can't take that
time away from the תורה. So the idea that you could be
held accountable for not achieving your potential in גמילות חסדים gemilus chasadim
the same way we get the message that you could be held
accountable for not achieving your potential in תורה, right, is a very
you know powerful message.
Well now I mean he's being killed for it.
Right, well as well or he's not being saved as an account
of it. Anyway he's not being killed for it, that's not what
the גמרא Gemara is saying.
אתיוהו לרבי אלעזר בן פרטא, atyu lei l'Rabbi Eleazar ben Perata, so
now רבי אלעזר בן פרטא Rabbi Eleazar ben Perata who is going
to be charged with five things but be saved, he was brought
forth. So one has to wonder from a dramatic point of view
what is the power of us knowing in advance that he's going
to be saved. You know what I mean? Like why was that
information given to us upfront? But anyway, so they brought רבי אלעזר
בן פרטא Rabbi Eleazar ben Perata there. אמרו, they said to him,
the Romans, 'מאי טעמא תנית?' mai ta'ama tanita? Why first of all
have you been spending your time learning like you know משנה, Mishnah,
learning rabbinic literature that's outlawed in the Hadrianic period? He's teaching it
right? Teaching it. Okay, right that's true teaching it. Thank you. 'ומאי
טעמא גנבת?' u'mai ta'ama ganavta? And also we have a report here
that you're a גנב. ganav. Now that's a bizarre, that's obviously a
trumped-up charge. Anyway, אמר להו, amar lehu, he said to them, this
is such a this is a famous line, 'אי סייפא לא ספרא,
isayfa lo safra, if the sword, not the book, ואי ספרא לא
סייפא, v'isafra lo sayfa, and if the book, not the sword.' So
as you can well imagine in Israel those that believe you're supposed
to be learning in ישיבה Yeshiva and not going to the army,
those who believe you're supposed to be going to the army quote
the גמרא right before and
תורה and גמילות חסדים gemilus chasadim serving the Jewish people. Those who
believe you're not supposed to be going to the army said either
the book or the sword. Make up your mind. So he said
obviously I cannot be both a גנב ganav and a sage. ומדהא
כדבא הא נמי כדבא, u'midahach la sa anami la, since one of
these charges is false, the other one is false too. Okay, so
clearly these are trumped up charges. And clearly I'm not a sage
either. 'ומאי טעמא קרו לך רבי?' u'mai ta'ama karu lach Rabbi? So
they said 'Oh so you're not a sage? Why are you called
Rabbi?' So
'רבן של תרסיים,' Rabban shel tarsiyim, meaning I'm a master, I'm a
weaver, I'm a master of weavers. Master craftsman, I'm a master weaver.
So oh you're a master weaver? Let's give you a little pop
quiz. So אייתו ליה תרי כיבורי, ayisu lei trei kivorei, they brought
him two spindles of wool. אמרו ליה, amru lei, 'הי דשתיה והי
דערבא.' hai d'shasya v'hai d'arva. Which one is the warp, which one
is the woof? I never know the difference either. I don't know
I always even forget which way where they mean. But you know
one of them is like laid out on the frame and the
other one the way they do they pick up the frame you
know it goes under and over and under and over but rather
than that's very time laborious, you know this was invented I think
in the modern era the what's it called the shuttlecock or whatever.
Anyway they pick it up they throw it and they put it
down. They actually have that in the משנה Mishnah on שבת Shabbos
a way of doing that. Anyway so one is the warp, the
other is the woof. So they said which is which?
שתי
וערב. shti v'erev. Okay so the שתי shti is the is the
base and the ערב erev is the one that goes through. Actually
that's a good way to remove it because ערב arev means to
uh okay okay. So anyway which is which is the warp which
is the woof? So איתרחיש ליה ניסא, it'rachish lei nissa, a miracle
occurred.
אתיא זיבורתא ויתיבא על דשתיה, asya ziburta v'asva al d'shasya, a female
wasp came and sat on the דשתיה, d'shasya, on the what do
you call it, on the warp, whatever the which one of the
דשתיה d'shasya is. ואתא זיבורא ויתיב על דערבא, v'asya zibura v'yasiv al
d'arva, and a male wasp came
and sat on the other one. Now how did they know this
and first of
all תוספות Tosafot says how can you or רש"י Rashi says how
can you... But anyway the point being the female one is indicating
the one that is sort of the one that is going through,
you know, if you think in a male sense, right, is penetrating
the female one. So the ערב erev was the male one and
the שתי sheti was the female one. Okay, so והיי דארבא? ve-hai
de-arva? אמר ליה, amar lei, so אמר ליה, amar lei, האי דשתי
והאי דארבא, hai de-shasya ve-hai de-arva, this is a שתי, sheti, this
is the ערב. erev. אמר ליה, amar lei, so they said to
him,
ומאי טעמא לא אתית לבי אבידן? u-mai ta'ama lo asis le-vei avidan?
Why didn't you have come to בי אבידן? Bei Avidan? בי אבידן
Bei Avidan was the meeting place and it seems from a גמרא
in שבת Shabbos that this was actually a place where they had
intellectual disputations and you know so it was like close to the
world of heresy because they were discussing religious issues, theological issues, religious
issues, philosophical issues. So some rabbis went and other rabbis did not
go because they felt that they would not be able to you
know articulate a good enough defense and you know and hold their
own well enough because that was not their field you know to
have these types of disputations, you know, and others did go and
others were concerned about being drawn after heresy. So there's a whole
interesting issues about whether rabbis participated in this or not. So why
did you not come to this house of disputation?
אמר להו, amar lehu, זקן אני והייתי מסתפינא שמא תרמסוני ברגליכם. zaken
ani ve-hayisi mistafina she-ma tirmisuni be-raglechem. You know, I'm so old, I'm
afraid that there's so many people there and so much crowding, I
would get trampled in the crowd. אמרו לו, they said to him,
ועד האידנא כמה סבי דאירמיס? ve-ad idana kama savy de-irmis? Have you
until now, you haven't heard of any elders that got trampled when
they went to this meeting place? איתרחיש ניסא ההוא יומא אירמיס חד
סבא, israchish nisa ha-hu yoma irmis chad sava, a miracle occurred today,
one old guy got trampled in the meeting house, ברוך השם. Baruch
Hashem. Okay, so he gets out of
charge number three. ומאי טעמא קשבקת עבדך לחרות? u-mai ta'ama kashvakt avdach
le-cheirus? Why did you free your slave? Maybe this had something to
do with the fact that it was שמיטה, shemitah, did they were
they נוהג שמיטה noheg shemitah at that time? You know maybe it
was a Hebrew slave, it was שמיטה, shemitah, I mean you know
maybe it was a non-Hebrew slave, it was יובל, Yovel, big question,
like were they נוהג noheg freeing of slaves at that time? But
anyway the presumably the Romans didn't want the Jews to free the
slaves, the Jews were still doing some freeing of slave, it was
seen as some religious practice. Okay, אמר להו, amar lehu, he said
to them, לא היו דברים מעולם, lo hayu devarim me-olam, never happened,
it's a lie. Okay, comes charge number four. קם חד מנייהו לאסהודי
ביה, kam chad mineihu le-ashodi bei, one of them got up, one
of the Romans got up to testify against him that I saw
that he freed his slave. אתא אליהו, asa eliyahu, another miracle occurred,
אליהו Eliyahu came, אדמי ליה כחד מחשיבי דמלכותא, idmi lei ke-chad mi-chashivei
de-malchusa,
he appeared like a very senior you know person of of the
Roman government. אמר ליה, amar lei, and he said to this guy
who was about to testify but appearing himself as a Roman, מדאיתרחיש
ליה ניסא בכולהו, mi-de-israchish lei nisa be-kuleihu,
since there were miracles occurred in the other things, you know being
able to see the warp and the woof, the old guy getting
trampled, so clearly God is protecting this guy. ובהא נמי איתרחיש ליה
ניסא, u-ve-ha nami israchish lei nisa, a miracle will occur to him
if you try to testify against him. ודוברא בישותא הוא דקא מחזית,
ve-duvra bishusa hu de-ka machzes, and you'll see in your own embarrassment,
don't do it, you're going to embarrass yourself, clearly his God is
protecting him. ולא אשגח ביה, ve-lo ashgach bei, this Roman did not
pay any heed to him. Okay, קם למימר להו, kam le-meimar lehu,
so he was getting up about to testify against him. הוה כתיבא
איגרתא, hava kesiva igarsa, now there was a letter that had been
was written, דהוה קאתיא מחשיבי דמלכותא, de-hava kasya mi-chashivei de-malchusa,
that important people of the government had written this letter, לשידורי לבי
קיסר, le-shidorei le-vei keisar, it needed to get to the Caesar, it
needed to get to Caesar in Rome. So as the day that
this guy was about to stand up and testify, they said who
can we send to go to Rome to bring this urgent letter?
Oh, this guy! Okay, and he said no, I have a court
date. He says no, tough luck, you've got to go bring this
letter. ושדרוה על ידיה, ve-shadruha al yadeih, and they sent him to
bring this letter to the Caesar, דהוא גברא, de-hahu gavra, they sent
it through him. אתא אליהו, asa eliyahu, now אליהו Eliyahu came when
this guy was on the journey to back to Rome, פטקיה ארבע
מאה פרסי, patkei arba me'ah parsei, and he threw him four hundred
parasangs, אליהו Eliyahu basically killed him. אזל ולא אתא, azal ve-lo asa,
he went but he did not come back, which a little bit
echoes כל באיה לא ישובון, kol ba'eha lo yeshuvun, right, those who
go won't come back. Anyway, so he got saved of charge number
four, freeing his slaves.
Okay, anyway, so wait, there was a charge number five, I somehow
missed him. Anyway, we'll go back and count them. So that was
the end of of רבי אלעזר בן פרטא Rabbi Elazar ben Parta
and he got saved from his five charges and we will see
tomorrow the story about רבי חנינא בן תרדיון. Rabbi Chanina ben Teradyon.